good morning everyone welcome to
meditating with Chandra Vicki so I'm a
cognitive psychologist a cognitive
scientist at the University of Toronto I
study scientifically academically
mindfulness and related phenomena like
Insight flow mystical experience
transformative experience the
cultivation of wisdom in addition to
that I've been practicing the past of
meditation Metta contemplation Tai Chi
Chuan Chi cung for 29 years over 29
years and I've also been teaching them
professionally for close to 20 years if
you're joining us for the first time you
of course welcome to stay but you should
know that this is a course so it's
progressive every Monday I teach a new
less than a new principle that builds on
previous principles so if you want you
can go back and go to my channel and go
to the playlist which is just the
lessons and you can watch the lessons
and catch up you're welcome to stay but
that's how you can catch up and be in
sync with everybody else and within the
course so on Mondays the teaching day
Tuesdays to Fridays but today we meet I
do a bit of a brief review we sit
together I answer questions there are no
classes on Saturdays and Sundays please
remember to turn in your phones to do
not disturb and I believe I'll just
quickly review what are the most recent
principle which is meta contemplation
meditation is stepping back and looking
at contemplation is trying to renew how
you see through we do that at the level
of our Co identification our existential
mode the we try to become aware of we
try to awaken to the process by which
were assuming identities and assigning
identities and then we try to awaken
from modal confusion confusing the
having mode
essential mode and being will be tried
to citee the word that's translated as
mindfulness which means to remember we
try to remember we try to have an
insight not at just the intellectual
level and inside that the existential
level that's the waking up to there were
member of the being mode because that is
the mode that affords development that
is the mode that affords transformation
that is the mode that affords the
aspiration and cultivation of wisdom one
question is just to be clear no matter
what you're doing always find the core
for and do a bit of a posture even when
you're going to sit for a meta sitting
you said I'm gonna do met it now right
first find your core for and do a bit of
a pasta two or three minutes and then go
into meta so you're welcome to dip today
to either do the past nut just all the
way through or do the core four do a bit
of pasta and then go into meta and then
after this we will of course have the
Q&A I'll try and pick up on some of the
questions that were left over from
tomorrow again if we don't get them all
today we will get to them throughout
this week all right everybody we will
begin when I say begin get yourself in
your your posture get it stable begin
you
integrate with your cultivated in your
practice with your everyday
consciousness and cognition remember if
you're doing Metta first Metta towards
yourself maybe the traditional phrase
happy happy and healthy happy free from
suffering
may be more recent phrase I realize is
such this more here do it which yourself
person you're close to going through
image of the name generic person in your
life person your conflict with and then
all beings or at least all people so
let's answer some questions semi and
Othman is it normal to see colors and
abstract faces yes that's very normal so
what's happening is some of the
machinery that starts to kick in when we
might be moving toward sleep visual
machineries PN seeing cars faces are
also very powerful because you need sort
of internal noise in your nervous system
can be interpreted it can often be
resolved into a face this is a very
normal thing to happen in meditation
just note it try not to get fascinated
by it these inner colors and these
interfaces can be very fascinating
they'll tend to lead you into sort of a
hypnagogic state and that could
potentially lead into you sort of
dreaming while you're still sitting so
it's normal try to note it and then
return to the breath I find my most
common distraction is storytelling this
is from Holly
hello again Holly running through future
conversations or potential scenarios in
my head this is very normal by the way
colleague running conversations one of
the most frequent forms of distraction
that's why I recommend not watching
movies listening to the radio listening
to music or talking especially having an
intense conversation right before you
sit while you're nervous
do you have any advice for this maybe in
mantra I'm going to next week Holly I'm
going to start teaching you how to
meditate
distractions so that's coming right now
I know this is a little bit sort of
right but if you could just keep doing
what you're doing
labeling the distraction and returning
to your breath labeling the destruction
returning she'd rather just keep doing
that and then next Monday and the
following Monday those two lessons will
be dedicated to how do we work with
distractions and one of the things we'll
talk about is how do you deal with with
something like that that sort of
incessant the monkey mind that is
basically that inner chattering speaking
line storytelling on running scenarios
what's happening
your brain is when you go into this
state now you're going into what's
called the default mode Network and that
is the network we do when we do is for a
mental time travel and we run scenarios
in our heads and have conversations it's
sort of it's at the core of mine water
and normally these two networks the
network that is involved with being task
focused and concentrating and being
oriented towards the world and the
default mode they they sort of switch on
and off in opposition and right now what
you're trying to do and it takes that
it's a bit of a you know it takes some
practice is you're trying to have them
Co active at the same time you're trying
to have all that internal awareness that
goes with the default of network but
you're trying to activate the task focus
network so you don't want to
mind-wandering because it looks like if
you could Co activate these that
actually forced the most and greatest
potential for transformation and
profound insight next one but suka
should we find the focus for some time I
am or could you raise the questions
please I can't see them all on my screen
suka is asking should we find a focus
for some time after finding the flow and
then go back to noting only in and out
with each breath that's exactly right
that's exactly right so once you've
found your focus by counting the breath
to get that set
or momentum of mindfulness a constant
renewal of interest you then just go
back then don't you following the breath
just with Internet that's exactly right
Lin Slater hi Lin it's a it's good to
see you again when I can't breath I have
a tendency to force it and I have to go
back to and I have to go back to just
focusing on the breath yeah
so perhaps Lin if you could do if
there's something else you could do
instead of counting the breath to try
and notice when you've had some
continuity some people I don't know why
this works
some people recite the alphabet ABCD
that seems to be to be different or just
by following the breath and maybe trying
to note right when you're distracted
right spontaneously oh I was I was with
my breath for you know the last minute
or two maybe try that as a maybe that
will get you out of that tendency to
control the breath Victoria my ex
student at Caen John explains such an or
detail yes such this is when you come in
to think about the think about the the
being mode so right now you know I just
have I just have this in my pocket but
if I step back and I start to relate to
this as like a work of art I start to
open up and I start to become aware of
how it has a presencing that is not
categorical and the nature the suchness
is the inexhaustible nosov this beyond
any of the categories by which i try to
capture it so as i start to unfold right
that the depths of all of this all of
its features all of its properties all
of those are categorical but I get a
sense I get a sense of the suchness I
get a sense of that about this that
transcends all of my identities that I
all the identities I assigned to it all
of the categories that I that I have
for in which I place it in order to
cognitively control and consume it like
bringing it into a category so when
you're trying to open up to the suchness
you're trying to open up to what this is
here now and in its we're the fullness
of its presence in and of course
everything has such nice and so there's
a sense in which the suchness is sort of
a focal awareness of the more Ness of a
particular thing so I hope that was a
little too abstract for you but so what
we're trying to do is which one right
and and notice again how you do have
that moments of profound love when you
realize that you're seeing your beloved
again for a newt like as for the first
time or that renewal because that's what
beauty does it makes us I've seen trees
before but I see this tree that's like
I've never seen trees before but of
course I I see this and so there's that
sense of us so much more I hadn't
realized and we remember the being of
something that's to try and relate to it
such nests all right so we'll take a
look at some more questions tomorrow
remember a continuity of practice more
important than quantity if you honestly
can only sit for five minutes
for five minutes try to alternate
between the pasta and meta but even when
you're doing meta first do the core four
do a bit of a pasta and then go into the
meta I want to as always thank the
techno major Mar and my beloved son
Jason please subscribe to the channel to
be notified of the next video and also
we if you like it's like you're joining
you can find all the teaching the
previous teaching videos there's a lot
of videos on there that are also really
helpful for the overall project of
cultivating wisdom and affording the
kind of resilient responsiveness and
objectivity for a current situation and
for life in general please invite others
who might benefit from this to join the
meditation course I'm doing this try to
help as many people as possible and you
can help me to help
if you reached out and told them about
this and encourage them to participate
we'll be doing this every weekday every
weekday from 9:00 9:30 est so thank you
everyone please keep up your practice
and I'll see you tomorrow morning take
care everyone
bye-bye